<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessednesse of a sound spirit: vvith the misery of a vvounded spirit VVhere first a sound spirit is described and differenced, and lets discouered, helpes prescribed. By Robert Harris.</title>
            <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839538</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839538</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3969</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02692)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1104:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessednesse of a sound spirit: vvith the misery of a vvounded spirit VVhere first a sound spirit is described and differenced, and lets discouered, helpes prescribed. By Robert Harris.</title>
                  <author>Harris, Robert, 1581-1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [at Eliot's Court Press] for I. Bartlet, and are to be sold at his shop in Cheap-side, at the signe of the gilded Cup,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of Harris's "Six sermons never heretofore published".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3969:1"/>
            <p>THE BLESSEDNESSE OF A SOVND SPIRIT: WITH THE MISERY OF A VVOVNDED SPIRIT. Where firſt a ſound Spirit is deſcribed and differenced, and Lets diſcouered, Helpes preſcribed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ROBERT HARRIS.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>I. Bartlet,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Cheap-ſide, at the ſigne of the gilded Cup. 1628.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3969:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3969:2"/>
            <head>THE BLESSEDNESSE: OF A SOVND SPIRIT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. 13.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The ſpirit of a man will ſuſtaine his infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie: but a wounded ſpirit who can beare?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is a ſhort Text, but excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding rich; the greateſt good and euill incident to man (in this life) are matched together. And it is done of purpoſe, that ſo each might illuſtrate other.</p>
            <p>The commended good is firſt deliuered in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> theſe words, <hi>[The ſpirit of a man will beare out his infirmitie:]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The diſſwaded euill is next ſubiouned, in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> theſe words <hi>[But a wounded ſpirit who can beare?]</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3969:3"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Subicctum pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatum.</note> In the firſt, wee muſt take notice what the thing is whereof <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes, and what it is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that is affirmed of it. The thing is <hi>[The ſpirit of man]</hi> man conſiſts of two parts, a body, and a ſoule; which ſoule ſometime from its ſpeciall ſeat is termed <hi>[Heart,]</hi> ſometimes from its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall office and effects, life, ſoule, breath; from its ſpirituall, is termed conſcience, ſometime from its cauſes ſpirit, (being for its matter not bodily, but ſpirituall) and for its originall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired and inbreathed. This ſoule and ſpirit of man being ſound and vnwounded (for ſo the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition leads vs to take it) doth beare vp and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> beare out its extremity: that is the ſecond thing, where euery word is weightie, and of great lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. The ſpirit (of man) of euery man (for ſo both Grammar and Logicke beare it here) bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth (with patience; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſtrength, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> comfort, conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, till it hath borne one quite through) his wound and maladie, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that which for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the diuine prouidence layes vpon him, his preſent burden (which euer ſeemes the foreſt) what euer it be, by whomſoeuer impoſed, how long ſoeuer it lie, whereſoeuer it light, ſo long as the ſpirits-ſelfe remains vnwounded, it wil beare it, and beare it againe moſt manfully, this the firſt thing the bleſſing commended, <hi>a ſound ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The miſery deſcribed and diſſwaded is a wounded ſpirit, oppoſed to the other: Firſt, in its affection (it is wounded, bruiſed &amp;c.) Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in its effect, it is vnſufferable, it cruſhes a man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3969:3"/>(any man) <hi>(who can beare it?)</hi> That is to ſay, none can. For ſo vſually (though not euer) thoſe Rhetoricall queſtions muſt be reſolued. If the queſtion be negatiue (ſo to ſpeake) the anſwer is affirmatiue, <note place="margin">Iob 31.</note> as in <hi>Iob</hi> 31. <hi>Is not deſtruction to the wicked?</hi> The anſwer implied is, <hi>Yes.</hi> Contrarily, if the queſtion be affirmatiue, as <hi>Who can beare it?</hi> The anſwer is negatiue, <hi>None can.</hi> The oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then is cleare, there is a ſpirit, and a ſpirit, comfortable, and broken; the one enables any (the pooreſt man) ſtoutly to endure any the greateſt miſery: the other ſo cruſhes the ſtouteſt, that he cannot ſuſtaine himſelfe without other preſſure in the midſt of all other naturall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and contentments.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, the Doctrine lies before you, <note place="margin">Doct. <hi>1.</hi> Propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> which is this: That a confortable ſpirit is vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable.</p>
            <p>As none other good can match it, ſo no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward euill can ouer-match it.</p>
            <p>There is a three-fold comfort and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which mans ſpirit is capable of. <note place="margin">Expounded.</note> One natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ariſing from the goodneſſe of mans natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> temper in body, bloud, ſpirit, and which is that which beares the vſuall name of cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            <p>A ſecond morall, ariſing from the exerciſe of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> morall vertues (eſpecially high and heroicall vertues) which breed a kinde of ſolace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment in the exerci<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, and worke delight.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Spirituall, ariſing from the preſence <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3969:4"/>and ſenſe of Gods holy Spirit curing vs, helping vs, and ſealing vp to vs the euerlaſting loue of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The point muſt be vnderſtood of this laſt, which excludes not the former, but eminently and vertually includes and containes them alſo.</p>
            <p>Thus then, that ſpirit which is ſupported by the Spirit of God, and comforted with the true conſolations of that Comforter, is inuincible: mans ſpirit (made comfortable with ſpirituall comforts) is vnconquerable. Indeed naturall <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hearefulneſſe may be ouertopt with ſorrow, comforts ſpringing from a faireneſſe of cariage, and freedome from ſtaring ſinnes may ſoone be daſhed, but ſpirituall comforts which grow from the apprehenſion of Gods loue, and are grounded and built vpon God, are impregnable.</p>
            <p>The heart fortified with theſe cannot be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly foiled; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Proned.</note> ſuppoſe rumours and ſeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege him. The peace of God, and his peace with God, keepes him in minde and heart, as ſafe as if he lay in garriſon, <note place="margin">Philip. 4.7.<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp;c. <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.7. He is as quiet as <hi>Eliſha</hi> in <hi>Dothus,</hi> or <hi>Danid,</hi> when in the middeſt of thouſands hee could ſleepe and wake; and wake and ſleepe againe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.5.6.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Suppoſe troubles throng in vpon him as faſt as vpon <hi>Iob,</hi> troubles in his eſtate, troubles in his houſe, troubles in his children, troubles in his body; ſo long as there i<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> peace within, hee can ſay, the Lord gaue children, the Lord gaue eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3969:4"/>the Lord gaue health, wealth, yea all hee hath, and therefore with <hi>Iob</hi> concludes, <hi>The ſame hand that firſt gaue, hath new taken, and bleſſed be that hand, Iob</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe hell is let looſe vpon him, and the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Deuiſl lets ſlip all his dogs at once, ſome barke, ſome bite, all chaſe and peſecute in all extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie; yet the comfortable ſpirit ſhrinkes nor, <hi>Paul</hi> is ſcoffed, he beares it, <hi>Paul</hi> is ſtocked, hee beares it, whipped, he beares it, ſtoned, he beares it: and how I pray you, with head and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? nay, with life and ſpirit: <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 2 Cor. 1.</note> 
               <hi>In all theſe,</hi> faith he, <hi>we are conquerours, and I reioyce in my infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as afflictions abound, ſo conſolations much more;</hi> yea he ſings: true, a <hi>Paul</hi> doth this; but who elſe, why others alſo, <note place="margin">Act. 5.4.</note> as <hi>Acts</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> Theſe are men of extraordinary ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but what doe ordinary Chriſtians? why, ſee in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10. They were flouted, reproached, <note place="margin">Hebr. 10.34.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, impoueriſhed, yet beare it, and how? with ioy. And <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. ſee how they were vſed, ſo perſecuted, as they were glad to liue in caues and dens of the earth, and wandered vp and downe in ſheepe-skins, and Goat-skins, and yet beare it, and ſtand it out: true, but why? becauſe they could neither will nor chooſe; no, they might haue beene deliuered vpon conditions, but they would not embrace libertie and p<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> vpon any ſinfull termes; ſo that whether they be euills feared, or felt, euils growing from out ſelues, or others; a comfortable ſpirit receiues
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3969:5"/>the charge manfully, and goes vnder the burden chearefully.</p>
            <p>The Reaſon why ſuch a ſpirit will beare its full burden chearfully, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> is becauſe it improues all parts, chiefly Reaſon, and that is a ſtrong bridle, which both checkes paſſion and vpholds the head. It is much that the Heathens endured by the power of Reaſon, a Chriſtian may doe more, becauſe grace refines and fortifies Reaſon, and cleares a mans ſight, partly by expelling the miſts that ariſe from the valley of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, partly by aduancing Reaſon to a higher pirch, for Reaſon and Grace differ in ſight as a high and low man, Grace being the taller lifts vp Reaſon, and makes it ſee ouer thoſe miſeries that reaſon of it ſelfe could ſee no end of, and hence perſwades patience.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> a comfortable ſpirit carries with it a good conſcience, confidence and boldneſſe; diſcouragement ſtill weakens: but a good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſends forth thoſe warming graces into the whole man (that is to ſay, Chriſtian courage, boldneſſe and the like) which keepe a mans head aboue water in all miſeries.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> a comfortable ſpirit hath a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent remedy if any thing offend it (as ſome ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes haue by vomitting) it runs to God, nor is it cloſe and reſerued (vnſeaſonably) towards Man, and ſo after ſome meanes vſed, it recouers it ſelfe, a good word raiſes the ſpirit thus vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it ſelfe, <hi>Prou.</hi> 12.25.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3969:5"/>
            <p> Fourthly, a comfortable ſpirit is not alone, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> a good heart hath the Word on its ſide, Chriſt on its ſide, and <hi>the Spirit of God helpes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. and <hi>the ioy of the Lord is ſtrength,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nehem 8.</note> 
               <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8. and <hi>the Spirit of God is a Spirit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1.7.</note> of power and ſtrength.</hi> We ſee Satans ſpirit can breake thorow many bonds (as in the Goſpell) benum a man in greateſt torments, (as in ſome Heretikes) how much more then ſhall that ſpirit, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Gods Spirit, breake thorow all?</p>
            <p>But as we muſt note the reaſon why, ſo wee ſhould haue noted aboue the extent, how farre the ſpirit ſuſtaines a man: Firſt, Generally in all things touching his calling and condition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: Firſt, as a man. Secondly, a ciuill man. Thirdly, a Chriſtian man. More particularly, it vpholds him in being, and keeps out death till it may depart with honour. The ſoule it ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts with its treaſure and paſſes through all pikes home to heauen, and leaues the body not without hopes of following it in due time.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it vpholds him in libertie, though <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the outward man be reſtrained, yet the ſoule knowes not what captiuity meanes, in deſpight of all encounters it will to heauen and there be free.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it vpholds one in confidence, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> makes him ſay, <hi>Yet there is hope:</hi> and, <note place="margin">Ezra 10.</note> 
               <hi>Though hee kill me, yet I will truſt in him, <note place="margin">Iob 13.</note> I will not forſake my vprightneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3969:6"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, it vpholds him in chearefulneſſe: as the mother cannot but ſmile in the morning, if the childe laugh vpon her, though ſhe haue had a tedious night with it; ſo Gods childe cannot but laugh vnder all, if God ſmile vpon him, and pull vp his feet as <hi>Iacob</hi> did when he lay a dying. In Gods light, he ſees light in greateſt darkneſſe, and the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of God is more to him <hi>than corne and oile,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. Pſalm. 63.3.</note> yea than life it ſelfe: <hi>ſhew vs thy face and we line,</hi> ſaith the Church often, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 80.</p>
            <p>See firſt (for humbling) whence our foiles and failings ſpring, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> not from the greatneſſe of our afflictions, but from the faintneſſe of our ſpirits: ſo that hence we may. inferre for our ſelues, what <hi>Salomon</hi> doth for others, <hi>If we faint in the day of trouble,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prou. 24.10.</note> 
               <hi>our ſtrength is weake:</hi> indeed when the childe ſtumbles, he blames not his owne feeble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but outward impediments: ſo we, when in ſickneſſe we fret and chafe, when in paine we rage and cry, when in pouertie we ſhrinke and ſhiuer, when in perſecution we quake and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when in our callings we faint and droupe; we doe not looke inward and obſerue the guile, guilt, vnſetledneſſe and feebleneſſe of our ſpirits, but runne outward to the occaſions, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine: Our ſickneſſe is ſuch, as none can beare; our paine ſuch, as none can brooke; our ſtates are vncurable, our incumbrances vnſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the miſeries and troubles wee are put vnto intolerable. Iuſt like the ſore childe, who cries out of his ſhooe, when the fault is in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3969:6"/>the foot; and the ſicke patient, which faults his bed, when he ſhould his backe. For firſt, what ſaith <hi>Salomon, The ſpirit of a man</hi> (rightly orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) <hi>beares his wound:</hi> if ſickneſſe be the wound, a good ſpirit will beare it, if pouertie, if diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, if impriſonment, if fire, a good ſpirit will goe vnder all. There is no gulfe ſo deepe, but a good ſpirit will thorow it; no mountaine ſo high, but a good ſpirit will ouer it. Next, we ſee <hi>Salomons</hi> words verified in many inſtances; <hi>What wound hath not a good heart borne heretofore?</hi> ſpeak of pouerty, ſome haue ſung vnder it; of paine, ſome haue laughed at it; of impriſonment, ſome haue reioyced in it; of flames, ſome haue em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced them with cheerefulneſſe. Whence then is it, that where others ſing, wee weepe, where others reioyced and triumphed, we are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſheartned and diſcouraged? Is it becauſe our miſeries and trialls are greater than others? Alas no, they muſt not bee brought into any compariſon with other mens, with <hi>Iobs, Pauls,</hi> the Martyrs. Whence then is it? truly the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction growes from the Inſide, they were vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, we guilefull; they were at peace with God, we are vnreconciled; they were filled with the treaſures of wiſdome, faith, zeale, and the like, we are empty; they were rauiſhed with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of God and conſolations of the ſpirit, wee are vnacquainted with them; they were armed with the power of God and patience of Ieſus Chriſt, we are naked; they kept themſelues in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3969:7"/>the loue of God, wee interrupt our peace and make a breach into our conſciences. Hence they looked vpon Men, Lions, Deuils, with an vndaunted countenance, and walked thorow rackes, and gaoles, and gyues, and deaths, and hells, without ſtartling, and we flie when none purſues vs, and quake at the ſhaking of a leaſe: oh now ſee your weakneſſe and ſay, my griefes, my troubles, my burdens be not greater than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but my truth, faith, humility, peace, ioy, patience, courage, comfort in the inward man is leſſe than others, elſe I might beare my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſith a good ſpirit will be, as <hi>Simon</hi> to Chriſt, his Croſſe-bearer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> it may ſerue for inſtruction; hence learne <hi>Pauls</hi> art, how to beare any thing: a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians dutie ſtands in theſe two things: Firſt, to doe any good: Secondly, to beare, if need be, any euill: this latter is hard, but not impoſſible to a man-like ſpirit; there is an art of bearing worth the ſtudying, ſome men deſire to know all things, ſome to doe any thing, but he is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt to ſpeed beſt, that can endure any thing, that can with <hi>Paul</hi> abound and want, <note place="margin">Philip. 4.</note> be in good and euill report, can be ſicke, can be pained, can looke vpon fetters, and whips, and ſtockes, and ſtones, and deaths as <hi>Paul</hi> could; he is a happie man whom God will not hurt, whom men, nor deuils, nor things preſent, nor things to come can hurt; labour to be thus happy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But you will ſay, how ſhould wee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to it?</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3969:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Why get a good ſpirit, firſt naturally good, a chearefull ſpirit. That, if a man be ſicke, is a medicine, ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> a good cordiall. <note place="margin">Prou. 17.22.</note> That, if a man be poore, is a continuall feaſt; <note place="margin">Prou. 15.15 23.</note> if pained, is health to the bones, eſteeme of that as of a great mercy: A nimble hand, a nimble foot, a nimble eye, a nimble wit, a nimble tongue is good, but a nimble ſpirit is better; therefore if thou haſt that, be thankfull and chearefull, if thou haſt it not, endeuour to get it, and being dull, whet it. Secondly, ſpiritually good; nature may be ouercome, that is as the ſtring of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument which ſnaps in two, if it be ſtrained too high: thus ſome croſſes are too hard for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for nature hath its latitude, as a bow its compaſſe, and muſt not be ouer-maſtered. But ſpirituall ioy cannot be loſt, <note place="margin">Iohn 16.</note> 
               <hi>none can take it from vs, Iohn</hi> 16. It cannot be vanquiſhed, it is ſtrong; therefore get this, and keepe this, which that you may doe, thus doe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if you will haue ſpirituall ioy reſt with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> you, you muſt diſlodge and diſcard two home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Inmates; as firſt, carnall delights; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſinfull luſts. Firſt, take heed of entertaining carnall delights, reſt not in wealth, truſt not to men, rely not on wines, meats, muſicke, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, company, &amp;c. theſe will deceiue in times of diſtreſſe; beſides that, nature quickly putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and turnes to corruption, and ſo proues banefull.</p>
            <p>Secondly, take heed of ſinfull luſts, theſe are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3969:8"/>ſo farre from bringing peace to the ſoule, as that <hi>they warre againſt it,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith. They are ſo farre from comforting, that they oppreſſe, as our Sauiour Chriſt teacheth; <note place="margin">Luke 21.34.</note> the end of this mirth is heauineſſe of ſpirit, <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> ſorrow, feare, anguiſh, tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and wo vpon euery ſoule that ſinneth, &amp;c. Therefore conceiue of ſinne (yea euery ſinne) as of a diſeaſe, a wound, an enemie to peace, and complaine and ſtriue againſt it, for ſo long as ſin is reliſhed, no peace nor ſtrength can be had.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, (theſe two euills purged out) thou muſt apply thy ſelfe to means of comfort, <note place="margin">Of meanes of comfort, ſee more Pſal. 43.</note> which giue, firſt entrance, ſecondly accompliſhment to thy comfort. Of the firſt ſort, our Sauiour in the fifth of <hi>Matthew</hi> mentions theſe: <note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, pouerty of ſpirit, a man muſt firſt ſee himſelfe deſtitute of all good, and meanes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, and be emptied of the creature.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, he muſt mourne, for that leads to true comfort, godly ſorrow lets in ſpirituall ioy.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, he muſt be m<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ke, and put vpon him a reſolution of ſuffering any thing for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſake. <hi>of god</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, bring good affections to all Gods ordinances, and draw waters with ioy out of Gods ſauing wells, <hi>Eſay</hi> 12. and drink of Chriſts wines, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.4.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Laſtly, he muſt get faith in Chriſt, caſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon Gods mercies in Chriſts merits; and thus it is gotten.</p>
            <p>Now in the next place care muſt be had to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3969:8"/>keepe this life of ſpirit, as well as to get it; and to doe that,</p>
            <p>Firſt, a man muſt keepe himſelfe vnſpotted of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſinne, and not returne to folly; but if he be ſoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſtill waſh, make euen by euening, as in the Law.</p>
            <p>Secondly, walke in truth and faith, ſtill exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> faith (to begin with that firſt) in meditating of, and applying the promiſes generall and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſtill walke in the light, and keepe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thy ſelfe in Gods preſence, <note place="margin">1 Iohn 1.</note> ſo peace ſhall be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, and the ſpirit will be held vp in cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, is nothing heauie, nothing better, a man ſhall be able to goe thorow fire and water.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> this is for comfort to thoſe that haue ſuch a ſpirit; natural courage and chearefulneſſe carries one thorow many things, ſpirituall cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage carries thorow all; that which nature (fleſh and bloud) quakes at, grace will trample vpon; nature ſhrinkes at paine, grace beares it; nature yeelds to ſickneſſe, grace ſtands it out; nature buckles and bends vnder griefe, grace ſwallowes it vp; nature quakes at death, trembles at the racking of the ſinewes, breaking of the bones, broiling in the fire, and the like, and cries out, Oh it is intolerable; grace ſpeakes in his words, I can doe any thing through Chriſt that ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens me, <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>And when it is put to it, then it workes moſt powerfully, a Chriſtian neuer knows his ſtrength
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3969:9"/>(rather Gods ſtrength) till hee be put vpon it, then he findes that tolerable, which he thought to be intolerable, and there meets with greateſt comfort, where he expected leaſt, and as a man in bed (whileſt he plods on the ſtormie weather abroad) thinkes it not to be endured, but when bee is one in it (what with buſling, what with cloathes) he paſſes thorow it; So it is here, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Oh the ſtrength of the ſpirit, it is great, he is ſtronger that is in vs, than he that is in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Magna eſt vis conſcientiae in vtram<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> partem. cis.</note> Oh the power of conſcience both wayes, as it makes a happie eſtate miſerable, if bad; ſo, a miſerable condition bleſſed, when good.</p>
            <p>Oh the conſolations of the Lord, they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable: the rage of fire, beaſts, men, deuills, &amp;c. doth not paſſe vnderſtanding. Reaſon can fadome finite things, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9. Philip. 4.7.</note> but the comforts of God paſſe all vnderſtanding: wee cannot conceiue how a man ſhould beare ſuch things as ſome haue borne; but we ſee they did beare them, we ſee our ſelues borne thorow thoſe things, which we thought before vnſufferable. Therefore reſt on God, hold your hearts in peace with him: Reioyce in him, and your ſpirits and Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (ioyning together) will beare any burden that hee will lay vpon you; his promiſe is paſt, you ſhall not bee tempted aboue your ſtrength, <hi>1. Cor.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> bleſſe God for a good inſide, you that have it euer bleſſe him for a purified conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a quiet ſpirit: this is your life, your meat,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3969:9"/>your ſtrength, your all in all. This makes the Chriſtian laugh better cheap than another, beare with more patience than another, liue with more comfort, dye with more confidence than another: while the heart is whole, all is well. Therefore if without thou finde no money in purſe, no friend in Towne, no eaſe in body, no comfort in life; yet findeſt faith, patience, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods loue within: reioyce in thy eſtate, bleſſe God for it; the eſtate is as the man is, the man is as the minde is, and as is the ſpirit; a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſpirit makes a comfortable eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But how ſhall I diſcerne betweene na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and ſpirituall comfort?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Spirituall cheerefulneſſe comes, firſt, from faith in Chriſt. Secondly, from loue to God and Saints. Thirdly, begets boldneſſe in prayer, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>Beſides, naturall chearefulneſſe may be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topt by euils: Firſt, Naturall, for our weakneſſe makes vs more ſenſible of ſorrowes than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts. Secondly, Carnall, for all ſinne is as poiſon to the ſpirit. Thirdly, Diabolicall, not ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comforts.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, a naturall ſpirit beares ſome things only, as <hi>C. Marius</hi> the cutting of his fleſh, but not all, as diſgraces, &amp;c. witneſſe <hi>Cato, Saul.</hi> &amp;c. Secondly, a naturall ſpirit, though it bite in paſſion, yet is deſtitute of poſitiue ioy, peace, confidence, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3969:10"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3969:10"/>
            <head>THE MISERIE OF A WOVNDED SPIRIT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. 18.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>A wounded ſpirit who can beare?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>Thus farre of a good Spirit: now to the bad.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Wounded ſpirit is a burden intolerable; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> before I proue the point, I muſt ſhew you that mans ſpirit is ſubiect to wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of two ſorts: Firſt, of a friend. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Secondly, of a ſoe. When God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> wounds as a friend (as often he doth afflict the ſpirit, as well as the body in loue) he makes that wound tolerable, partly by qualifying, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigating the blow (for in wrath hee remembers mercy) and whereas thoſe inward wounds ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3969:11"/>degrees (as pricking, breaking, opening the heart) he proceeds not to extremities with his children, partly by ſupporting with ſecret hopes and comforts, for his childrens peace is neuer quite taken away, faith neuer quite failes them: but when he ſmires as a foe, the wound proues vnſufferable to a creature, and ſuch as would ſoone ſwallow a man, did not the Lord ſuſtaine nature to beare it, he could not elſe ſtand vnder it. Indeed when God proceeds to wounding, the ſpirit would vtterly faile, did not either mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or iuſtice in God vphold it in being.</p>
            <p>Now that a wounded ſpirit is a burden into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, we will proue from teſtimony and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Teſtimony: Firſt Diuine, here in the text, and elſe-where, <hi>All the dayes of the afflicted are cuilt:</hi> which if it be true of other, much more of this affliction that falls vpon the ſoule, <hi>Pron.</hi> 15. 15. Secondly, other teſtimonies, namely, from thoſe that haue had experience of it: as 1. men, and there, Firſt, good men: How haue the ſtou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt yeelded vnder this burden? How hath it ground them to duſt? Heare <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 32. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. His bones were broken as it were: How made it <hi>Iob</hi> to wiſh death? <hi>Iob 6.</hi> to quarrell God; others to quake, <hi>Pſal. 77.</hi> to howle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102. nay ſome to attempt death, ſome (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to effect it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from bad men, how doth it terrifie them, <note place="margin">Leuit. 26.</note> ſo that they fly at a leafe; paine them, that they caſt vp all their ſhame; and how doth it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3969:11"/>them not only of outward comfort, but of life, and cauſes them to caſt themſelues into hell to auoid it? How haue they wiſhed thouſands of yeares in hell, ſo that then they might bee eaſed?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Deuills; they witneſſe this truth againſt their wills: Firſt, when (their conſciences being terrified at the fight of Chriſts God-head) they cry out, <hi>Art thou come to torment vs before our time;</hi> and quake as priſoners when they ſee the Iudge comming. Secondly, When God purſues them, very anguiſh and ſorrow makes them madde, and to loſe all vſe of their large vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings; when they would ſting Gods creatures to death, and doe him and them the greateſt deſpight, they endeuour the troubles and terrours of conſcience, as well knowing this to be the moſt cruſhing and preſſing euill.</p>
            <p>Thirdly of Chriſt Ieſus, who though free from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſinne inherent, yet endured the ſorrowes of death, and was broken not in body only, but in ſpirit alſo, when he cried out <hi>(My God, my God, why haft thou for ſaken mee?)</hi> and trembled, and ſweat, and bled, and groned vnder this ſtroake, which was ſo intolerable to Chriſt Ieſus, as that the Angels of heauen came to comfort him, and the Godhead was requiſite to ſupport him, who can ſtand vnder? In ſhort, wee haue heard of creatures that haue ſuffered the mangling of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the ripping vp of bowels, racking of ioynts, burning of fleſh, boiling in oyle, and the like,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3969:12"/>without crying out <hi>(My God, my God, why haft thou for ſaken me)</hi> but neuer heard of a wounded ſpirit, but either it ſunke vnder deſpaire, or made pitious moane to God, or man, or both.</p>
            <p>Firſt from the cauſes of this wound (as it is mingled with ſinne) mans ſelfe and Satan ioyne, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> and theſe be ſore enemies; Satan is a fiery Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, a ſtinging Serpent, a cunning deſpightfull Aduerſarie, and yet he is the leaſt: when a man is diuided againſt himſelfe, and wit, knowledge, memory, ſtrength, all the weapons of nature and the enlightning ſpirit, are turned againſt ones ſelfe, it muſt needs be tedious and bitter: but then as theſe wounds are fruits of Iuſtice, they are properly Gods ſtroakes; and ſo there is not <hi>Dauid</hi> and a <hi>Goliah,</hi> nor <hi>Dauid</hi> and a <hi>Saul,</hi> a King and a Flea oppoſed, but the Creator and creature. <hi>is God</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> from the effects, it diſableth, or diſcourageth a man from the meanes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; of all diſeaſes, thoſe be worſt, which make one vncapable of Phyſicke, depriue one of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or of ſtrength to take helpe: ſuch are theſe of the ſpirit; A man labouring vnder this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and inwardly bleeding, is afraid to pray, to communicate himſelfe, he thinks that he tempts God in it, that his phyſicke is his poiſon, at leaſt that it will be to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it multiplies feares, creates feares, euer doubts more is behinde that which is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die felt.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3969:12"/>
            <p> Thirdly, drawes matter of diſcouragement and feare from all things, as we finde in all ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; if God feed, it is but to fat him for the knife; if he preſerue, it is but for further iudgement; and ſo of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, from the ſubiect, the ſpirit is the life <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of all: as the light of the eye is the light of the hand, of the foot, and of all the parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſo the ſpirit is the life of all; no life in wealth, friends, eſtare, &amp;c. without this; this runnes thorow all; wound this, wound all, yea this is the pillar that beares vp all; as when the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke failes, legs, armes, and all parts faile; ſo when the ſpirit failes, all failes: and as in a houſe where is but one getter, iſ he ſinkes, all ſinke: ſo here, it is the ſpirit that purueyes and brings in all, if this pipe be ſtopped, no comfort ſtreams toward vs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> this diſcouers the miſerable folly and wickedneſſe of moſt men, who of all burdens ſeare and feele this leaſt. A wounded eſtate, a wounded name, a wounded body is ſomething with them; but a wounded ſpirit they know not what it meanes; hence this laſt is neuer fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when the other worke trembling, nay hence conſcience receiues wounds on the inſide, that the ourſide may be ſaued: men will ſteale to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent pouertie; lye, to get out of debt; conſult with Wizards, to eſcape ſickneſſe; they will giue their ſoules a thouſand gaſhes to faue the skinne. Oh intolerable folly; this is to pricke
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3969:13"/>the hand for the ſauing of the gloue, nay to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard ones head, for the ſauing of a hat, of a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: of all enemies God is the foreſt; of all wounds his the deepeſt; of all parts, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and ſpirit the tendereſt: ſo long as there is peace within, peace with the conſcience, peace in our affections, peace with God, with Angels, with creatures, with the Word, ſo long a mans burden (be it what it will be) is tolerable; but when God fights againſt vs, and there is a pitcht field within vs, that our owne eyes, and mouthes, and hands, and wits, and ſpirits be againſt vs; Oh then who can beare it? a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded name, a wounded eſtate, a wounded legge, a wounded arme may be borne; but when God breakes the bones within, when our owne thoughts and dreames amaze vs, and wee be a terrour to our ſelues, and our conſciences be wounded, what is then left to comfort vs? whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt a man hath ſome friend, there is ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; whileſt ſome meanes of comfort (ſome parts and places whole) there is ſome refreſhing, but when no one part is well, no one place can eaſe him, no one minute is free, no one friend ſtands for him, no one creature is comfortable to him: who will not pitie ſuch a ones eſtate? This the ſtate of the wounded ſpirit; this wound as it is piercing, ſo ſpreading, it goes thorow all the man, head, heart, ſide, backe, all parts ake and ſweat whileſt the ſpirit is racked; the eye ſees no comfort, the tongue taſtes no comfort,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3969:13"/>the eare receiues no comfort; all is bitter, bitter to the whole man, and the ſtouteſt man in few dayes is but a liuing carcaſſe or skelleton; as there is no eaſe within, ſo no comfort without, no place (nor bed, nor boord, nor houſe, nor Church) no creature (nor mear, nor drinke, nor friend, nor wife, nor childe) will afford any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. All aboue vs, all below vs, all about vs, all vpon vs, all within vs, makes then for terror and miſery, nothing at all for eaſe and comfort. Oh conſider this, you that make nothing, or but a ieſt of Conſcience, and care not what yee ſay, what yee doe, how many Sabbaths you breake, how many lyes you tell, how many oathes you ſweare, how many men you couſin, how many ſinnes you ſwallow, ſo you may preuent out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward miſeries; know, there is a wound of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience beyond all wounds, a miſery of ſpirit beyond all miſeries, a breach of the ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all breaches, and either wound your ſelues with ſhame and ſorrow for theſe wounds, which you haue giuen your ſoules, and condemne your ſelues for fearing debt, or ſhame, or any trouble more than conſcience, or elſe know that the ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt conſcience ſhall be once awakened, the hardeſt heart once broken, and brawnieſt ſpirit once ſoftned; and then you ſhall finde a weight beyond the weight of mountaines lying vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and wiſh that you had beene rather famiſhed, or ſterued, or burnt, or ſtrangled long before, than euer you ſhould liue to know
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3969:14"/>what a wounded ſpirit meanes; beleeue it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, howſoeuer you finde for the preſent an euill conſcience no burden, yet before you and it part, you ſhall finde <hi>Salomons</hi> words true; <hi>A wounded ſpirit who can beare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> if conſcience be wounded, make forth to haue it healed; we ſeek skill in ſore eyes, and mouthes, and the like, let vs labour for skill alſo to heale conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To this end, Firſt, know the time of cure, <hi>viz.</hi> preſently: greene wounds are ſooneſt cured; as therefore the Toad poiſoned runnes to her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, and each creature to his; ſo let him that hath his conſcience wounded, get a healing po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſently.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, know the medicines and meanes of cure. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ignat. ad Polyc. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Satan</hi> is a Mountebancke, as appeares by his Apothecaries: ſome preſcribe poyſons, as if <hi>Similia ſimilibus,</hi> as Papiſts heale a conſcience with treaſons: ſome preſcribe toyes, as outward things, drinkes, muſicke, and the like; ſome thinke to out-wraſtle conſcience, as they doe ſickneſſe, but this diſeaſe will not be oppoſed, neither will any medicines cure it, but onely Gods, and they in briefe are theſe, Faith, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and (in ſome caſes) Satisfaction; for this know, as when an officer is wounded, two things muſt be done; firſt, Authoritie and the State muſt be pacified; ſecondly, the wound cured: euen ſo here, Conſcience is an officer, firſt cure that; ſecondly, God and man too (ſometimes)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3969:14"/>are treſpaſſed, they muſt be ſatisfied. Now the way to ſatisfie the offended, is, firſt, ſubmiſſion, ſecondly, either ſubſtitution or reſtitution.</p>
            <p>In ſinnes immediately againſt God, we muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt get a Suretie, Chriſt Ieſus, ſet him betweene God and vs: and there muſt come in faith, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. till wee beleeue, wee bee in our ſinnes: <note place="margin">Iohn 8.</note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we muſt ſubmit, firſt confeſſe our ſinnes, take ſhame to our ſelues, reſtore Gods glory; ſecondly, reſigne our ſelues, and humble our ſelues vnder his hand, <note place="margin">Iames 4.</note> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> 4 lay our neckes on the blocke, and here comes in Repentance and Reſtitution.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in ſinnes that immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> man, the ſame path muſt be trod, firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in diuers caſes (goe to thy brother if he haue ought againſt thee) and ſecondly Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in <hi>Numb.</hi> 5. <note place="margin">Numb. 5.</note> If thou haſt runne away with this good name, reſtore; if with his goods, bring them backe againe: and here note, that the nearer the tye is, the worſe the treſpaſſe; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the childe that robs his father, is a greater theeſe <hi>(cater is paribus)</hi> than he that robs by the high-way: ſo the wife (howſoeuer nature giues an intereſt in goods for proper vſe, and contract more according to particulars agreed vpon, and ſomething may be preſumed vpon where is no exception) yet for wiues to giue where is no need, againſt husbands minde, beyond his eſtate, and ſo forth, is vtterly vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider the method &amp; order of cure, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:3969:15"/>ſtill we muſt to God, he is offended, he only can worke peace, therefore we muſt looke to Chriſt the Braſen Serpent, and weepe ouer him; but yet if man be treſpaſſed, wee muſt firſt to him: God would haue his worke tarry, till there be a purpoſe (at leaſt) of being reconciled to man: therefore be firſt reconciled; ſecondly, deſire his prayers, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> laſt.</note> as <hi>Iobs</hi> friends did his. Thirdly, apply to conſcience, as hath beene ſaid, firſt plucking forth the ſting of ſinne, then waſhing in Chriſts bloud; and for the future, keepe the heart aboue all keepings, as yee doe the eye in the middeſt of chaſſe and duſt; for as the eye is ſubiect to infinite diſtempers, ſo is the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, there is a diſquieting of the ſpirit, which vſually proceeds from vnwatchfulneſſe, and that in three caſes; Firſt, when a man guards not the heart againſt euery ſinne, for ſinne hath a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting nature, and is fretting like poiſon. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, when hee neglects meanes of comfort (as the ſtomacke is troubled with ouer-faſting) or elſe, thirdly, vſes them ſleightly and formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: ſo the ſpirit waxeth firſt dull, ſecondly ſad, thirdly ſorrowfull, as the Apoſtle implies in his Epiſtles; therefore watchfulneſſe muſt be vſed in things ſinfull, lawfull, and indifferent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, there is a perplexing of the ſpirit, and that ariſeth from ignorance, and that in three caſes: Firſt, when a man hath no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the Word, darkneſſe makes one feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3969:15"/>and cauſes errour. Secondly, when his conſcience ſeemes to be greater than his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as in ſcrupuloſities. Thirdly, when hee cannot put a difference betweene himſelfe and Satan in his temptations and abhorred ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions; <note place="margin">Of this ſee notes on <hi>Iames</hi> 4.</note> hence come horrours perplexities, theſe muſt be preuented, Firſt, by ſticking only to the Word which ſets our bounds; Secondly, by get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting knowledge in the Word, <note place="margin">Philip. 1.</note> and a diſcerning ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there is wounding of the Spirit, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> is vſually done by ſinnes againſt light and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: there is a threefold light belonging to Gods children: Firſt, one of nature which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, ſinnes againſt this ſting, as vnnaturall luſts, murders, &amp; the like. Secondly, one of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and acquired (rather reuealed) light, ſinnes againſt this wound ſo much the more, by how much the more cleare the euidence is; the moſt euident truths are the firſt principles (which proue, but need no proofe) thus, firſt, it is a ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne to deny the Scripture; ſecondly, to reuege expreſſe truths therein contained, or to diſobey things daily vrged: thirdly, of grace or infuſed light. Thus when a man ſinnes againſt knowledge, purpoſe, vow, grace receiued; this is fearfull, and makes many thinke, that their ſinnes are vnpardonable and againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, there is deading and ſearing of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ſpirit: as the body is ſubiect to two kinds of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3969:16"/>and maimes, ſome that affect and afflict ſenſe, ſome that depriue of ſenſe, as violent blowes, palſies, &amp;c, ſo is the ſpirit alſo. Now this is the moſt fearfull caſe of all, and comes to paſſe three wayes: Firſt, when men commit ſome horrible ſinne which ſtrikes out the eye, or layes one for dead, like a blow on the head. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, when they ſhunne all meanes of awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning conſcience, runne from the Word, from Saints that admoniſh, from thoughts of death, &amp;c. Thirdly, when they force conſcience, and vſe all meanes to ſtop its mouth, and to cruſh it for euer: this is as ſearing after cutting, when a man neuer meanes to haue the part againe, but to take away all ſenſe; feare theſe diſeaſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> this may be for comfort to thoſe whoſe conſciences are not wounded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> What is the difference betweene a ſpirit healed, and a ſpirit deaded or deluded?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Looke to the meanes and medicines healing, whether our peace ariſe from faith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, the word. 2. A healed conſcience is pure and cleare throughout, the other ſpirits make no conſcience at all, or onely of ſome things. <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.21.</note> 3. A healed conſcience makes interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories to God, firſt if doubts ariſe, it ſaith as <hi>Rebecca,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Why am I thus?</hi> and prayes to God; the reſt are ſtiffe, and ſhun all queſtions. 4. A hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſpirit pities others; in this caſe the dead heart cannot abide the name of conſcience, but ſaith
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3969:16"/>(as <hi>Pilate,</hi> what is truth? ſo) what is conſcience? the deluded ſpirit is fierce towards all but thoſe that be of his minde, as all Heretickes and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes proue. Now if our pulſe beat right, and we haue the comfort of a ſanctified conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, keepe it, by two meanes: Firſt, by ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, a man muſt deny himſelfe in his meanes (riches, friends, &amp;c.) Secondly, in his hopes and owne worth; firſt, be nothing in himſelfe; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, expect all from Chriſt; thirdly, in his ſenſe and feeling, he muſt winke and put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into Gods hands, that is, liue by faith, as <hi>Luther</hi> did, reſt on the naked Word without any pawne, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Pitie the wounded ſpirit; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> if we heare that a man hath broken his leg or arme, we pitie him, how much more ſhould we bleed with the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart and bleeding ſpirit; and furniſh our ſelues, firſt with wiſdome, that ſo we may be able: ſecondly, with loue, that ſo we may bee willing to ſuccour ſuch, <note place="margin">See notes on <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 43.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. but more of this elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: therefore here an end.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
